All right, well, welcome to problem session 5 of 6 .006.
It's a pleasure to see all your smiling faces here today.
This week, we're going to cover some problems in graph theory related to
depth first search and breadth first search, which were roughly the topics
that I guess we've covered in the last couple of
lectures and what's going to be on your homework.
And I believe this is basically the
homework from last year with a few
revisions based
on some typos we cut.
Oh, and I caught a spelling mistake that
I'll bother our instructor about later.
OK, so without further ado, let's get started. I guess we'll just do them
in order for lack of creativity here. The very first problem has to do with
some measurements on a graph,
which is actually a really interesting one to
me. So it turns out that in a lot of research in,
for some reason in computer science, there's graph theory research
and then there's networks research. And these are two different
communities for weird historical
reasons that I don't totally understand.
But people in the network science literature often measure things like the
radius of a graph and some other kind of measures that are trying to tell
you something about like is a graph a long spread out thing like a line
graph or something super compact like a star and so on. And so this problem
is kind of digging into the algorithmic aspects of how
we might compute one of the measurements that I believe
is
fairly common in that community.
So let's kind of go through these problems.
As usual, in 6 .006, we like to take
actually relatively straightforward computational problems and then dress
them up with a lot of language to make it annoying for you guys to parse.
And indeed, this problem is no exception to
that.
So in this problem,
we're given an undirected graph.
And as usual, we will
call him g.
And we define a particular number that we're trying
to measure in this problem. So in particular,
if we're given a vertex v,
then we can define something called the eccentricity of v, which
is the distance to the farthest away thing. So in particular,
we can define
given by the following,
which is the max
over all the possible.
I'll try to
make sure my notation.
Oops, I've
already. Oh, that's OK.
Over all the
other vertices of the distance from v to w.
So I'm standing at a point on a graph. And now I make a loud noise. And the
last person to hear me, the distance to him would be the eccentricity of
that vertex.
And so this is some kind of notion of radius or diameter, but sort of
planted at a point. And then if we want to learn a property not of a vertex,
but of the entire graph,
one thing we can
do is define the radius.
And that is given by r of g is the min over
all of the different vertices u
of the eccentricity of u.
OK, so I think this is one of these definitions that's really annoying to
parse and think about. So we should draw a little bit of a schematic and
see what's going on here, because especially as a geometry professor, this
one's kind of nice because it translates directly to what you might do in
metric geometry.
So let's say that
I have a circle here.
And I want the world's most complicated way
of defining its radius.
OK, so for any given point,
there's a point in a circle. That's a circle in case you're wondering. You
know those internet contests where they have people that just walk up to
the board and draw perfect circles and then
leave? I unfortunately
am not an expert at this matter.
But anyway, so if we think of a point, like a circle, as some analog of
our graph, and then I draw a point, which might be the analog of a vertex,
then what is eccentricity? Well, it's
the distance to the farthest away point.
The length of this line, roughly, because
that's the distance to the farthest away thing.
So for every different
point that I draw,
each point has
its own farthest away point in the circle.
So there's some positive number that's assigned to every single point
in this domain. And if I take the minimum of that positive number,
where do you think I end up?
The center of the circle. JASON KURIYAMA - That's right, Jason. I end up
in the center of the circle, because if I think about it, the distance to
the farthest away
point in this domain,
one thing you can convince yourself is that
that's sort of as small as possible.
So this is what we might
call a minimax problem in optimization,
because we are minimizing
the maximum distance.
This also shows up in game theory, all kinds of different places that solve
this stuff. But thankfully, in this particular problem, we're not going
to need all that.
OK, so this homework
problem has two parts.
The
first is to give an algorithm for computing
the radius of a graph. And then the second one is to give an
algorithm for approximating the radius of the graph really quickly,
or more quickly than the
first part.
I actually don't know
if there's a lower bound there, but
come back to that later.
OK, so in part A,
we're given g. And moreover, we're given one additional piece of information,
which we actually do need in this problem. I think it's one of those
words that kind of slips
past us when we read graph theory problems.
But
it's important to pay attention, of course.
And that is,
we're given g, and it's connected. I suppose really
it should be given connected g, but that's OK.
Now what we want is to compute
the radius of g
in time that
looks like the product
of
the vertices, the number of vertices, oops,
times the number of edges,
or the number of edges times the number of
vertices.
Your instructor struggles to speak and write at the
same time, but it's a skill that I'm working on.
And frankly, handwriting
is much easier with this little chalk.
OK,
so essentially, I used to have a math professor
in college that used this phrase all the time.
It's important not to
think here.
The problem
asks you to compute the radius of a graph.
And in some sense, there's
an algorithm that just writes itself
for computing the radius. Right? Because the radius
is the min over all the vertices of the eccentricity.
The eccentricity is the max distance. So
what would be the simplest thing to do here?
Well, in some sense,
it would be to loop over all the vertices,
compute their distance
to all the other vertices, and take
the max for each one of those, and then the
min over all of the guys in the outer loop.
Since I just said a sentence that I'm realizing doesn't parse
particularly well, let's sort of write down what I mean,
which is to say,
we're going to think of the being an outer.
That's why we don't use this chalk. An
outer for loop, which is computing this min.
Right?
Well, what are we going
to do? We can compute
the shortest path distance
to all of the other w
in my graph.
You know,
take the max
of w of the distance from
v to all the other w's.
Obviously, we
can kind of do these two at the same time.
And then if this number
is bigger than my current max, keep it.
Oh, yikes.
If it's smaller than
the current estimate I have of the radius,
then I keep it. And if it's not, then I throw it away.
Right? So maybe I initialize my radius at infinity.
And now, let's call this number,
I don't know, little r.
If little r is less than big R,
then just keep it around.
Right?
And so if we think about it, I don't think it's terribly hard to prove
that this algorithm is correct, because it's sort of just taking our
definition of what the radius of a graph is and
translating it into a brain -dead algorithm.
So I think really the challenge here is proving
the runtime in this particular algorithm.
So what does our runtime
look like? So we have a loop over vertices.
Right?
So I kind of incur a factor of mod v here.
And then, well, our graph is unweighted. So one strategy for
computing the shortest path distance would be breadth -first search.
I think that's what's
in my notes. Yep.
And in general, breadth -first search, if you
recall from lecture, takes mod v plus mod e time.
So the question is, OK, so if I multiply
these things together, what do I get? I
get
O of v times
v plus e,
like that, time.
But like, uh -oh, that's not the time that
my homework problem wanted.
Right? Because the homework problem asked
you to solve this in just mod v times e time.
And somehow we've
incurred an extra factor.
And now we have to figure out why this is actually OK. Or we have to fix
our algorithm. But in this case, it turns out that this runtime is just
inaccurate.
OK?
What's our intuition here? Well,
I kind of underlined it
for you here. Our graph is connected.
In particular, there's going
to be a nice property of connected graphs,
which is that the number of edges
dwarfs the number of vertices here.
So really, if we have v plus e,
in some sense, this is going to look like a constant factor times e
plus another e here. So this whole thing is going to be v times e time.
Yeah, so let's make
that argument a tiny bit more formal here.
So
in particular, we
know that g is connected.
Right. And every vertex,
so in particular,
what can happen here is,
OK, unless
my graph consists of one vertex,
which is
a case you could dispose of pretty quickly,
what I can't have is a graph that looks like this, like one vertex and then
an edge floating around there. Everything has to be connected together.
OK.
So
in particular, what this means
is that
every vertex
is adjacent
to at least one edge.
Again, except, I guess, technically the one vertex case. But I think we
can convince ourselves that for any graph of constant size, we're not
terribly worried about it. Right? It's just
the asymptotics that matter in this problem.
OK.
So if every vertex is adjacent to one edge,
well, and remember that every edge, kind of by
definition of an edge is adjacent to two vertices,
then what we
can conclude is that the number of vertices
is less than or equal to the number of edges
divided by 2. This is a conservative estimate.
And so in particular,
what does that mean? It means
that v is big O of e.
This is a case where we have to be quite
careful about big O being an upper bound.
Right? In this case,
typically, v is much less than e.
Well, depends how many edges, like
if you have a really dense graph or not.
But in
this case, what does that mean? That means
that mod
v plus mod e is really just big O of mod e.
Because
this is big O of mod e plus big O of mod e.
And that means
that our
problem really runs in v
times e time, which
is what we wanted in our problem.
Are there any
questions from our audience on part a here?
Cool. Yes? I don't quite
understand why where you went from the first statement to the second statement
there. At most, one edge implies v is less than or equal to e over 2.
Oh, yeah. So I guess there's sort of two things that
matter here. Every vertex is adjacent to one edge at most.
And every edge,
yikes.
Every edge is adjacent to
two vertices.
I guess actually, it's the second one that matters. So
you can never have a vertex just floating by itself.
So one way that I can count my number of vertices by looking at the number
of edges and saying that, well, every edge can touch exactly two vertices.
Every vertex has
to touch exactly, well, at least one edge.
So if you put those together, you can convince
yourself that this bound has to be true.
If you want to be conservative about it, you can just get rid
of the divided by 2 here, I guess. It doesn't really matter.
Any other questions from
our audience?
Cool.
All
right. So now let's take a look at part b.
So in part b here, they ask us to basically do some version of the same
thing. They want us to now approximate the radius, but we're given a smaller
budget of time.
So now what we want
in number b here is
to compute an r star
such that I
got yelled at in my textbook that St apparently should always be subject
to. I got an angry review of the textbook I wrote because of that, which was
puzzling to
me. But amazon .com is
not a great source of useful data. But in any event, we
want r star, which is sandwiched between the radius of g
and 2 times the radius of g
like that.
Now, notice, so in
other words, we want to,
the first
thing you notice is we want to upper bound
the radius of our graph.
And already, this should suggest to us how we might solve this problem.
Because if we take a look back at our definition of radius over here, notice
that the radius is a min.
So what's going to happen
if I returned epsilon of some other vertex?
Well, it's lower bounded by the radius because the
radius is the smallest possible epsilon over any vertex.
That make sense?
Now, when I was doing this problem, because I'm
the dumb instructor of the three, I said, well, OK.
But maybe I need to be somehow
judicious about what vertex I choose.
Like, well, in some sense, what this suggests is that maybe I choose some
other vertex and compute its radius and return that as our approximation.
But of course, the problem wants me to sandwich it between two values here.
So in addition to upper bounding r, I want to be less than 2 times r. In
other words, my
approximation is within a constant factor.
I tried some weird stuff, like farthest point sampling
and so on. Then I realized that you actually don't really
need to do any of that. One thing
you can do is literally choose any vertex,
return its eccentricity,
and that's actually good enough.
So here's our algorithm.
Right, let me go
back to my notes here.
I don't know why I'm following my notes. I actually do this off the top of
my head. But they make me feel better if I'm looking at them at the same
time.
So in particular,
what I'm going to do is
choose
a u and v.
Let me be clear here.
Any
u and v. So if I'm using some data, data structure to
store all my vertices, I just take the first one, whatever.
And two,
I'm going to return
r star is equal to epsilon of u.
Now, of course, this isn't really an algorithm. If
you do this on your homework, you'll lose points.
And the reason is that
I haven't told you how to compute
this value here. So if you were to write out your answer for this problem,
of course, you should tell us that, like, really, to compute epsilon, what
do I do? I use breadth -first search to compute
the shortest path from u to all the other vertices.
And then
I guess I take the max value here.
OK, so I think you guys can fill
in the details of the algorithm.
The bigger challenge is going to be to
prove that this is actually a good bound.
And so
in other words, what we need to prove here,
I don't know, like there's a claim, there's a proposition, there's a
theorem. So we're somewhere on that axis. I'm going to call this one a claim.
Downgrade it.
And that is that
the radius of my graph
is less than or equal to r star,
which is less than or equal to 2 times the
radius of my graph. OK,
so let's prove this thing.
Managing to use all
of my boards on one problem here.
OK, so in particular, to prove this claim, I need to prove
two inequalities. This is like two homework problems in one.
So let's number those
off. There's 1. There's 2.
OK, so
let's do inequality 1.
I think we can squeeze
him into a relatively
small space.
So remember, what
is the radius of my graph?
Well, just by definition,
we know that it's the min.
Over all possible u of
epsilon of u.
So in particular, what's the nice property about the minimum
of something is that it's less than everything else or equal.
So this,
maybe let's call this u0 just to distinguish between
that and the notation I have on the left -hand side.
This is less than or equal to epsilon of u
because,
I don't know, because min.
Yeah,
so that actually already,
and of course, this
is exactly what we chose to be our r star.
So our first part of our proof is
done here. Yeah, so this is the easy part.
And sometimes,
this is sort of what inspired our algorithm. So we
expect this bound to be kind of straightforward.
OK, but
the other half of the
problem is a little more tricky.
And actually, there's a solution in the notes. And then I decided
just to make it a little more inaccurate to write up my own.
But actually, I have an ulterior motive, which is I noticed in this
class, we don't tend to use the tiny piece of notation that I like.
So for my convenience in future problem
sessions, I thought I'd introduce it now.
So we're solving
a minimization problem.
The nice thing is that in this class, everything we do is finite. If you
take my graduate course, that's not going to be the case. In fact, actually,
in lecture two, we're going to do
variational calculus. But in this course,
what does that
mean? That means if I minimize a function,
there's actually a vertex in my graph that
achieves that minimum.
This is different than, for example, if I then
I'll shut up. But if I wanted to minimize,
here's f of x equals 1 over x. And
I ask you for the minimum value.
Well,
it's overall x greater than or equal to 0.
Well, the minimum value is 0 if I take x off to infinity. But it
never quite crosses 0. So you're kind of in this weird universe.
If you remember Jason's lecture, he talked about
infs and supes as opposed to mins and maxes.
But this
can't happen in our problem. Because when we compute
a min, there's actually a vertex that achieves it.
And that vertex we call argmin.
And so
this arg here stands for argument.
So one thing that I can do is say,
OK, so remember that my radius is the min
over all u
of epsilon of u.
Then I'm going
to define a vertex u0
to be the argmin
over u
of epsilon of u. And this is just fancy notation for saying, give me
the actual vertex that makes this value as small as possible. Yeah?
The nice thing about this problem is that we're not worried yet about how
we make runtime. So I can construct this kind of thing and not worry about
how we actually found it.
OK.
So let's say that we did that. So this is, find me the vertex that actually
gives me the radius. So in other words, I find that vertex. And then I
find his or her farthest away vertex and measure the
distance. And that distance is the radius of my graph.
OK?
So let's actually do that. So in
particular,
then
I can define a second vertex v0.
Well, how does the radius algorithm work? I find the
central guy. And then I find the one that's farthest away.
So we're going to make him
the argmax
over all v in my graph
of the distance
starting at u to any v.
So
if I think about my circle, it's a circle.
Then u0
is like that center of my circle.
And then v0
is like that far away point.
This is a schematic.
My circle is really a graph in this problem.
But I think the analogy actually works.
OK.
But in reality, my algorithm was brain dead. I didn't actually compute
u0. I computed, I just randomly drew, sorry, I shouldn't use that word. I
arbitrarily drew a vertex u and then computed the farthest away distance
from that guy. And of course, what we have to check is that that thing is
within a factor
of 2 of what I wanted.
So OK. If I have u, then I'm additionally
going to define one more thing called v.
Oh,
boy.
So I'm noticing I'm saying
one thing and I'm writing another.
u0 is the center of my graph.
I think I said it. I just forgot to write it. And then this v is the
farthest away guy from him. So basically, the subscript 0 here means is the
platonic ideal of what I wanted in my problem.
And no subscript is going to mean the other one.
So now,
I compute the farthest away thing from the u that I
actually chose in my algorithm. That's some v bar.
So again, remember, my algorithm just says, OK, I'm going to choose some
other point v and then return v's distance to some farthest away point.
Oh, sorry.
Choose another. Oh, boy.
Choose a point u
and return his distance
to some far away point v.
I think I've
managed to lose everybody.
I'm nodding together using these
here.
So why did I introduce
all of this notation?
Because this is what's going on in this problem. To actually compute the
radius, I want to find the most central point u0 and its distance to its
farthest away thing v0.
In reality,
I arbitrarily chose a
point u. And I returned u's distance
to some point v. And I want to show that those
two things are within a factor of 2 of each other.
OK. That summary makes sense, even
if I talked in circles for a while.
OK. So let's actually do that.
So remember that the thing that I'm going to actually return is r star. And
that is equal to distance from u to v now, because I just made all these
definitions.
And now, I get to
use my favorite inequality.
In fact, this is sort of the only inequality we know in this class so far,
I think, which is the triangle inequality, which says that, of course,
this
is less than or equal to the distance from
u
to u0 plus the
distance from u0 to v.
So in other words, this is saying the shortest path from u to v is always
upper bounded from the length of the shortest path from u to u0 and then u0
to v. This is drawing
a triangle.
Aha.
But take a look. What is
the actual radius of my graph?
Well, in my notation,
the
radius of my graph is exactly the distance
from u0
to v0.
And this thing
is bigger than the distance from
u0 to anything else by definition
for all of you. Right?
So if
I flip this inequality backward,
well, take a look. This is the distance from u0 to something. This is
the distance from u0 to something. So I incur two factors of the radius.
And I get the
bound that I want to.
Yep.
And so this is a slightly more formal proof of
exactly the same thing that's in the homework notes.
OK. So the one thing that's remaining is to
actually show that our algorithm
runs in a reasonable amount of time. So I
think they give us a budget of order e time.
But notice that argument is precisely the argument
that we just made right here, just minus the v factor.
And the v factor just came from looping
over all the vertices in part a.
Now I think we're
done with problem one.
As usual, I've wasted too much time on the
easy problem.
All right. Any
questions about this one?
Excellent. Well, now that I've written too
much,
let's do the rest of it.
I spent time on this problem because I
like it. It looks like a geometry problem.
OK.
So now, let's see. In problem two, which I noticed that this homework is
kind of full of prototypical 6 double 6 slash graph theory problems in
general. They just go down the list of things that people
typically do in graph theory that are useful tricks to know.
So
I would suggest the students in this class,
even if it's pass -fail, look very closely at this homework before doing
the current one. I think the ordering works out that they can do that.
Because I
think you'll get some good hints
for how to solve
all the current homework.
So you
heard it here first, guys.
OK. So in problem two,
we're talking about
internet investigation.
So in particular,
MIT
has a bunch of different routers
that are connected by
cables to one another.
And essentially, what are we given? We're given a bunch of different
routers. And we're given the length of the cable in between them.
And the latency, unsurprisingly,
is proportional to the length of the cable.
In my abstract understanding of how computers work, it kind
of makes sense to me. I'm not sure that's actually true.
But
that's sort of immaterial
for 6 double 06.
I assume our department has a networks class,
if you're interested in that kind of thing.
And essentially, what we're trying to do is sum up the latency over all
of the routers. So let's write down a little bit of notation here while I
continue
to dance all over the room here.
I keep losing my chuck.
Need like a holster. I feel like
that would be useful for the chuck bucket.
So now we're going
to do problem two here.
So we're given R routers.
And some of them
are marked as entry points.
Because of this,
so technically, I think a lot of students in this class have encountered
weighted graphs before. But if you think about the narrative of this course,
I think for the version of this homework, we haven't really encountered
weighted graphs yet. But a better way of putting it, rather than
psychologically diagnosing
your instructors,
is that what we're going to find is that there are often problems that look
like they're weighted graph problems, but they really aren't. And this is
a nice example
where that's the case.
OK.
So we define latency as
follows, that it's at least proportional to
the shortest path to an entry point.
And now we have two additional assumptions
that we need.
One is that the total latency,
or at least the latency
of every vertex,
which is
the same thing, latency,
is less than infinity.
What is this really saying? By the way? When would the latency be infinity?
It would only be infinity if I took a pair of scissors and cut a wire and
just connected from
the rest of the network.
Yes?
Every router is connected to some entry point. That's exactly. There's some
path from every router to some entry point. Doesn't necessarily mean the
entire graph is connected, I guess. But at
least you can always get to an entry point.
And then moreover, and this one's the real
kicker here,
that there's at most 100 R feet of
wire.
Incidentally, R stands for routers. I had the previous
problem in my head and was thinking radius a long time.
So don't be like your instructor and actually read the entire problem before
getting hung up on it. But in any event, the thing that you're trying to
do is to compute
the sum.
Over all of the routers,
I don't know, R, whatever,
of the latency of that router.
So that's our problem here. Incidentally, this little goofy exercise I
just did of taking this paragraph problem and writing it in bullet points I
find helps me a lot when I'm trying to solve these algorithms problems
because I think it's really easy to just get thrown off by a wall of text
here.
So
this problem is screaming out graph theory.
Like using the terms here. We are using the terms, right? Like you've got
nodes that are kind of like routers and maybe edges are kind of like wires.
But there's a bit of a catch, which is that your runtime,
right? At the end of the day, I think you want order R runtime.
That's
where things get a little funky initially.
And so we have to think
a little bit carefully about how to do it.
And here's
going to be the trick.
So this is starting to look like a shortest path problem. What would you
maybe not want to do would be to iterate over every single router or every
single vertex and every single router and compute
the shortest path between every single pair.
Because if you did
that, oh boy, I'm confusing my terminology.
There are entry points, which is the thing
that I need to compute the distance to.
And I need to iterate over every single router and compute its distance
maybe to all the entry points and then take the min or something like that.
But if I had a double for loop, then I'm
probably not going to get order R time, right?
Somehow you expect it to look like something
squared or like the product of two terms.
So it's going to be a little more sneaky than that.
And we're going to use sort of a canonical trick
in graph theory.
OK. So let's follow the Toucan Sam approach here. We're going to follow our
nose and say that, OK, there's basically a graph that's staring us in the
face in this problem.
But then we have to make a little bit of an edit
because we'd like to use the kind of linear looking time
search that BFS
affords us. But it looks like we have edge
weights in our graph, right? Because the wires
are associated to lengths,
right? Different wires
have different sizes.
But we have this nice fun fact, which is that the total
amount of wire in our whole universe is less than 100R.
I guess the units of this 100 are kind of weird,
right? It's like feet per router or something.
But whatever.
OK. So in particular,
I'm going to make a graph.
With
a node
per router,
right? So maybe here's a router.
There's another router.
There's router
1 and router 2.
But since I want to use the sort of linear time advantages
of breadth -first search when I'm computing distances,
I can be a little
bit sneaky about this,
which is to say instead of having like 10 feet
of wires, I'm going to have 10 one -foot wires,
yeah?
Except
now I'm additionally going to have
little chains. So here
maybe the length L12 is equal to 3, right?
So I'm going to put
three edges in between.
So in other words, I'm
going to connect them
with
chains
of Li edges
for each wire.
Does that make sense? So essentially, I'm going to take my weighted graph
problem and make it unweighted by just like repeating a bunch of, well, not
really repeating, but
chaining together a bunch of edges
so that the total length of this thing is equal
to the distance from one router to another.
OK.
One thing we might as well do is bound the number
of vertices and edges in our graph when we do that.
So first of all,
let's think about
the number of vertices.
And we can be totally lazy and
upper bound this stuff. It doesn't matter.
Well, for one thing, I have one node per
router. So we incur one factor of r there.
And now notice that we're kind of laying down cable
one little piece at a time here in our chains.
And now I always tend to have a fence post
style
headache about exactly what the constant factor
is here. But if we're conservative about it,
we incur at
most a factor of 100 r
kind of additional edges because those are all the different pieces that
we could lay together. I think it's actually less than that because of the
endpoints.
But whatever because r plus 100 r is big O of r. So
the number of vertices in my graph here is big O of r.
Similarly, what's the
number of edges?
Well, this is exactly the amount
of cable that's inside of my network,
I believe. Yep.
Right. So this is exactly 100 r.
Well,
I guess the way the problem is written,
it's upper bounded by 100 r, but whatever.
So this again is big O of r.
This is kind of convenient. So now we have one number that rules them all,
which is r. Which tells you both the number of vertices and the number of
edges up to a constant factor. So one thing I can convince
myself is if I do BFS on my graph, that's sort of OK. Remember,
that's vertices plus edges time.
But in this
case, those are the same.
OK.
So remember,
at the end of the day, I'm trying to compute the latency. This
is like the length of the shortest path to the entry point nodes.
So here would
be a brain -dead algorithm, which would say
for
all routers,
for all entry points,
compute, I
don't know, let's call the router on i, the
entry point j.
I compute distance i, j, like using breadth
-first search or something.
And then I take the min
of these values.
And
add them all
together. So I compute
for every router. I look at every possible entry point. I compute its
distance to the entry point. I take the min over all these things.
And now I add
that to my running sum.
There's a problem here, which is I haven't told you the
relative number of entry points to the total number of routers.
So at least the
way that I've written this algorithm here,
how much time would this take?
Well,
there's two different for loops.
And in the worst possible case, at least in my brain -dead algorithm, I
don't notice that if I am an entry point, then I don't need to compute
distances.
Well, this would
take order r squared.
Whoa.
r squared time,
right?
At least, right? Actually, I
shouldn't even write big O. I should write,
what's lower bound? Oh, god. I'm a terrible
algorithm professor.
Omega
of r squared time, because I haven't even counted for the
amount of time I need to take to compute the distance.
And this is a problem because I've only given
you a budget of linear time for your algorithm.
So this is frowny face.
I tried drawing the turd emoji on my notes,
and it really didn't work.
So we need a better trick.
And this is
actually one of these prototypical tricks,
which is to do the following.
So let's construct a graph. I'm going to draw my graph in a particular way.
But notice that there's nothing about my algorithm that cares about the
way that I drew it. This is just to make my
life easier,
which is I'm going to put all the entry points on the left
and all the remaining non -entry point routers on the right,
because I can.
And so this is what my graph looks like. So
these are my entry points.
Here are my other routers.
My graph doesn't have to be bipartite. It could be
that my routers are connected to each other, whatever.
I go from my entry points to
the routers in the graph. I'm trying
to make sure that my graph is connected.
OK.
And so essentially
what this problem is asking you to
do is to say, OK, for every single node in my
graph, I need to compute the distance to the closest
entry point and then sum
all those things together.
That's the
schematic we could have in mind.
So
in some sense, what we want to do is think
about the set of entry points as one giant node,
because it doesn't matter which of these guys I choose for
my shortest path to an entry point. I just need to find one.
And so here's the basic trick. And this is one that appears all over graph
theory, which is I'm going to introduce one additional node to my graph.
And I'm going to put him on the left -hand
side.
He's really big,
because he is a supernode,
which is a term of art.
This term shows up
a lot. And I'm going to connect it to every
entry point
in my network of routers.
Does that make sense, class?
OK.
So here's the kind of cool thing. So first
of all, for every entry point,
what's the shortest path from the entry point to the supernode?
Well, obviously, it has length 1. I drew it for you here.
Now,
here's the thing. Let's take the shortest path from the
supernode to any of the routers on the right -hand side.
How do I know? Well, clearly, maybe
I choose this guy here.
Well, what is my
shortest path? It goes here and then there.
There's one property that matters here, which is
that it has to pass through one of these entry nodes.
Which one does it has
to pass through?
Shrug.
For shame.
Well, remember,
Justin's favorite
inequality is the triangle inequality.
And what does it say?
It says that if I compute the shortest path
from the supernode to
any node in my graph,
then every subpiece of
that shortest path is also a shortest path.
That sentence was hard to parse. Let's try
that again.
So in particular,
if I have a graph from
the supernode to some router over here,
well, we've convinced ourselves it
has to pass through one of the entry nodes.
Which one does it have to pass through? Is it ever
something that is farther than the closest entry node?
Well, no, because I could compute a shorter path in that case by
choosing the closest entry node and then going to the supernode.
So this is a complicated way of
saying that essentially what we really want
is
for every router,
the distance
from that
router, let's call it i,
to the supernode s.
Is that quite right? Is that the
distance to the closest entry point?
You went one more inch too far. I went one inch too far, right? Because I
went to the closest entry point, and then I took an additional edge. So we
want to do minus 1.
OK.
So what does this mean? Well, that means that I don't actually have to
have this inner for loop over all the possible entry points. I just need to
construct this new special graph with one additional
node. Notice it's not going to affect my runtime.
And compute the shortest distance from the
supernode to every other node in my graph
and then use that as my output.
Yeah? So in other words,
what is
my algorithm going to look like?
Well, first,
I'm going to construct my graph. So what do
I need to do?
If I were to write this out on my homework, I'd have to talk about how I've
got these chains of edges between different pairs of routers. In addition
to that,
I'm going to make one additional supernode
and insert an edge from that to every entry
point.
Notice
that adding the entry point here just adds a 1 to the number of vertices
and at most, I guess, an r to the number of edges, which doesn't
affect asymptotically the size of either
of these two sets. So that's a good thing.
Now I'm going to use BFS to do
single source shortest path
from my supernode
to all other vertices.
And how much time does
this take?
Well, remember that in general, BFS takes v plus e time. In this
case, v plus e are both look like r. So this is order r time.
OK?
And then finally,
I'm going to sum over
routers i,
the value of the distance
from the supernode to the router i minus 1 to account for that
additional edge that I added. OK? And that's the solution to our problem.
OK. Any questions about number 2
here?
Excellent. Go team.
OK. So now let's
move on to problem 3.
Am I? Yeah, we're about halfway.
OK.
So problem 3,
right. So we're doing
Patry Harder
and three wizard friends.
The number
3 here, I believe, is actually irrelevant.
Although, like, any time you see a specific number in a problem, you should
cache that in your bag of things to remember. And in this case, that was
a red herring.
Patry Harder and
her three wizard friends
are tasked with searching around
a labyrinth.
Yeah? And in particular, there's some nice things
to know about the labyrinth and Patry Harder world.
This is really throwing
off my dyslexia here,
which is the following.
Right.
So what do we know? We know that there are
n rooms in my labyrinth.
And that each of my rooms has,
at most, four doors.
OK?
So in other words, if I think of building a graph out of my rooms, which is
like, I don't think I'm giving much away about this problem by jumping to
the solution a little bit. What do we know about the degree of
any vertex, assuming my vertices are rooms in the labyrinth?
It's at most 4. So that's kind of
nice.
Right. And all
the doors start closed.
So that seems like
a useful piece of information to remember.
But we have this kind of weird thing, which
is that some doors
are enchanted.
And apparently,
Patry Harder can open up certain doors for free, which are not the enchanted
doors. And then other ones, they have to do the blessing and the holy
water and whatever it is that happens in this universe and then opens up
that door. But that costs them materials and heartache. Right? And so we
want to minimize that.
Right? And so what they're given
is basically a map.
Right? And this includes all of the different rooms, how they're
connected to one another, and which of the doors are enchanted.
And what I want
is the minimum number
of doors that they have to disenchant.
OK?
Now, this
problem is kind of sneaky.
The reason why is that there's the network
that's obvious to build.
And that turns out to be not quite the right one. And then you can start
thinking about adding weights on your graph and going crazy with that. But
that turns out not to
be the right direction.
And in fact, in Patry Harder world, apparently, we're
not worried about their physical fitness. In other words,
shortest paths are actually irrelevant
in this problem. Do you see that?
Because let's say that I have
a really complicated, annoying problem. Or
maybe I have, here's my labyrinth.
And no,
we don't even talk about the entry point, like where they actually go in.
But just for fiction purposes, let's say that they enter my labyrinth here.
And just to be annoying,
the two doors that are enchanted, remember, we could make a
graph where all the vertices are rooms and the edges are doors,
are at these two endpoints of the T. So I have
a giant T, and I enter right in the middle.
Now, what is
Patry Harder to do here?
Well, obviously, since this graph is
a tree, there's only so much they can do.
Maybe they enter here.
They walk all the way to the end
to disenchant the
door over here. And then they turn around,
walk
to the other end, they disenchant that guy.
And now they
can reach other rooms.
Yeah, because that's their goal, to visit
every room. Sorry, I think I skipped that step.
Now, there's a few things to notice about this example, which make
it a little bit different from the typical graph theory thing,
which is once they disenchant this
door, they walk over here and they open it.
Well, now they walk over to this other room just to, you know, it's like,
you know those gym exercises? You run to the other side of the room, you
touch the floor,
and then you run back.
That's kind of what they did here. They ran to this room, they tapped
that vertex, and now they want to turn around and walk to the other side.
So once they open that door,
it stays open.
And
that's actually quite important,
because what it does is it makes this problem not look like
a traveling salesman problem, which wouldn't be so great.
OK,
so right, and moreover,
does the fact that there's like, maybe I subdominate these
edges. I have a bunch of edges here that are all not enchanted.
Does that matter?
Like if I had like
5 billion edges here?
No, right, because they only ask in this problem for
the minimum number of doors that you have to disenchant.
Yeah, so it might be the Harry Harder walks really far along my graph,
but as long as they don't walk through an enchanted door, it costs them
nothing.
So what does that mean? Well, that means that like in some sense, the second
that I enter a room, I might as well walk to every other room that it's
connected to through unenchanted
doors,
and that doesn't cost
me anything. Right, so sort of as a policy,
I should do that, right? I enter a room, and then I kind of just search
around and enter every possible door that I can that doesn't cost me an
enchantment, because those are free, and my
goal is to visit every room. Yeah,
OK, so here's going to be the sneaky trick.
Like what is that starting to smell like?
I open a door, and I want to explore all the other rooms
that are connected to that one. Maybe a connected component?
Yeah, maybe a connected component. There's a
problem. Is a connected component in this graph?
Well, no, like this whole
graph is one giant connected component.
So the sneaky trick is we're actually going
to remove
the enchanted doors that we're supposed to
erase, and it didn't happen.
But the point is that if we remove the connected doors, these are
like the chunks of my map that I can visit without incurring any cost.
So if I think of my graph,
maybe there's like a bunch of vertices over here, and then there's an
enchanted door, and there's a bunch of vertices over here, and then like two
more enchanted doors like that.
And like what goes on in here, like if
this is like a giant triangle or something,
is actually irrelevant,
because once I touch any one of these,
I can now touch
all the rest of them.
So that's just an algorithm. So
our first step is to construct
a graph G where the nodes are
the rooms.
And what should the edges be?
Well, if I'm just trying to find these little clumps of
rooms that I can visit for free if I get to any one of them,
then the edges
are the non
-enchanted doors. OK?
And so now in step two,
I'm going to compute my
connected components,
which we covered in lecture,
the connected
components of my graph G.
How much time does that take? Well, remember that there
are two different algorithms we mentioned that can do this.
This is full BFS or DFS.
And both of them
are going to take the same amount of time.
What is that time?
Linear in the size of
the graph. Linear in the size of the graph.
OK, so initially, that
could be problematic,
because I want
order n. Remember, there are n rooms here.
But thanks to our degree bounds, thanks to
knowing that every room has at most four doors,
you can convince yourself that both the number
of vertices and the number of edges are order n,
which I should probably rush through,
because as usual, I'm going slowly.
OK,
so now what do I have? I have a list of all
the connected components in my graph.
And each one is potentially connected
to some other ones by enchanted doors.
So in some sense, I could
think about
this not as a solution to the problem, but I could think
about modeling my problem as making some new graph,
or like I put a giant vertex.
And every connected component.
And maybe I connect them by enchanted doors. And I
want a path that touches every one of these rooms.
But that's not quite the
right way to go.
And this is what catches me by surprise, because this starts sounding
scary, right? If you've heard of the traveling salesman problem, it kind of
smells like that.
But that's not actually correct
here for two reasons.
One is that once I open an enchanted door,
I can go back through it. I can hopscotch back and forth through that door
as many times as I want, and it doesn't cost me anything. It only cost me
something the
first time I open it.
Yeah?
And moreover, I didn't ask you to actually
compute me that path.
If you read the problem closely, it just asks
for the minimum number of doors you have to open.
So this is a
really sneaky problem,
because it turns
out there's additional
one line of code that solves this problem. That's step three, which
I'm going to write before steps one and two, just to keep you confused.
Is to return
this number
of connected components minus 1.
That seems sneaky. Why is that? Well,
what's going on here is the following,
which is that, let's say that I walk along. Remember that my graph is
connected. So what I know is that I can always get from any one connected
component to any other.
And so let's
just take whatever order.
Notice that the problem hasn't actually asked me how to return an efficient
path. It just asked me for the minimum number of doors I have to open.
So all I have to do is convince myself there exists a path with this many
doors I have to open. I don't have to actually return it. If I did, it
would be mildly more annoying to
think about.
OK.
So my graph is connected. So one
thing that I could do is make the world's,
like,
well,
how do I want to do this?
Well, let's see here. I
guess I could come up with an ordering that
looks like depth first search of my graph.
That should do it.
OK. So maybe I started this
guy. I just started some arbitrary vertex.
I'm going to do depth first search. But rather than on the full graph, on
this kind of meta graph where I've clumped together rooms that I can get to
with no cost.
So what am I going to do? I'm going to start walking outward toward this
guy. And then in depth first search, backtracking and then going back down.
And if you think about it, remember that in depth first search, I have
this property I never need to revisit a clump which I've got to at once.
Well, the total number of doors that I'm going to open is exactly the
number of connected components minus 1 because as soon as I've done that, my
depth first search is done here.
In other words, that's the number of nodes
in my graph.
So if I took,
what would be a better way to,
I'm noticing that in my head this
was easier to articulate than in words.
Here would be a way to do it.
Would be
maybe add some more enchanted doors to the graph. Maybe add some more
enchanted doors. That's true. Actually, my problem is a little too easy.
So as long as my depth first search backtracks along the path that's already
found, then I'm reaching out into this tentacle, and then reaching back,
and then reaching to a new place. I'll now traverse an enchanted
door that I don't need to because I've already seen the location.
Is your traversing a tree? Yeah.
I've got
a shortest path tree that's going on here.
Actually, I guess a breadth first
search would be a better example.
In fact, here's, OK, let's be concrete about it. I'm sorry. I should
have thought about this more carefully than I did at home yesterday.
One thing I could do would be to compute a
shortest path tree from one vertex in this graph
to all the other ones.
Shortest path.
And I could traverse that tree to one node,
and then traverse it all the way back,
and then traverse it to a new node, and then
traverse it all the way back, and so on.
This is not an efficient path from a walking perspective. But from a
door opening perspective, it's extremely efficient because it's a tree.
And remember that the number of edges in a
spanning tree of my graph is exactly the number
of vertices in my graph minus 1,
which is exactly the property we have here.
Sweating for a second there.
OK.
So now in our remaining 30 minutes here, we've got
two more problems, which is more than enough time,
especially because the
last problem is
largely combinatorial and less algorithmic.
So I think it's OK to focus,
maybe talk about that
at a high level and show a fun plot.
OK. So for problem four, we have
an airline,
Purity Atlantic.
That's cute, Jason, really.
And it's owned by Richard Ransom. Did I get
that right?
And Purity Atlantic has
a cute sail.
This is not like
a cute angle, I suppose.
Which is essentially the following, which is that you can book an itinerary
where you have your home city, and then you choose, I believe, three
other cities
that you want to visit.
And then Purity Atlantic,
maybe you're on your honeymoon, and you're
not concerned with price,
but rather just the efficiency because you don't want to spend your
whole time in an airplane. That's particularly true this month.
Then what do you want to do? You want to minimize your total
number of connections, right? Because as we all know in
spring 2020, we don't
want to spend very much time in airports.
Yeah?
So right.
So how do we do that?
Well, we make a website where
you tell Purity Atlantic the cities that you want to visit in your home
city, and they give you back an efficient itinerary that minimizes the number
of connections.
OK. And the question is,
how do you actually do that, right? How do you compute the best
itinerary that minimizes the number of flights you have to take?
So what are our variables? And sometimes it feels like the variables are
all the different permutations of the cities you could visit, right? I could
go to,
I don't know, Cambridge, Boston, and then Cambridge in the UK. Maybe you're
doing a university thing, and then, I don't know, Budapest and some other
place. Or I
could do those in any other order.
And that feels like it should be factorial,
which would be bad news.
But this is one of these problems which I suppose a computer science
theorist might call fixed parameter tractable, but that's sort of an overkill
term here. But essentially, as long as you ignore all
the factors that make this problem hard, then it's easy.
A different way to put
it is that, OK, if I'm
only visiting cities,
what's the total number
of possible orderings of my three cities?
Class.
So I have city A, B,
C. I could do B, C, A. I could do B, A, C.
Listen up.
JASON KUOCHILAWAEGAWAEGAWAEGAWAEGAWAE Yeah,
fine, Jason.
I'll do that.
So
this is what we call direct
proof mathematically,
which are all the possible ways
to visit three cities.
And now, by my direct proof, I claim there
are no other ways to visit three cities.
And in particular, there are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6 different
orderings of the
cities that I can visit.
Notice that this is a constant in my problem. I
am not asking you to make a website that takes
the total set of cities that you want to visit as a couple and order
them. It's specifically 3. You might also notice that 6 is 3 factorial,
which is perhaps a more
efficient way to get to that same balance.
OK,
so right. So there's six different
orderings of the cities. And in each case,
what am I going to have to do? I'm going to have to
compute the sum of going from my source city to city.
From the first one to the second one, from the second one
to the third one, to the third one back to the first one.
So what
do I need? Well,
I need, in some sense, I want to be conservative about it, just the cost
of flying from every city to every other city. But that's not quite right.
I only need the cost of flying from every city that you have specified as
a city you're interested in to every other city that you specified that
you're interested in.
OK,
so in particular,
I go to my new one.
So in this problem, we
have c cities
and f flights.
OK, and initially, it might seem that
we have to compute a ton of shortest paths.
But if I
want to go from Boston to
Budapest to London to I'm running out of cities Paris and back to Boston
or whatever ordering I prefer, do I need to worry about the shortest path
from Nebraska to California?
Potentially not. That could be irrelevant. The only ones
that I care about are those four cities that I've identified.
OK, so there's three
factorial possible permutations.
And at the end of the day,
well, there's 2 times
4 choose 2.
If
you're wondering, this is 12 or big O of 1.
Pairs of cities,
meaning that
for itinerary purposes,
itinerary.
OK, meaning that if I always enter an airport
in one of city A, B, C, or my hometown,
and I
always exit through another one,
so then there's four possible
cities. I choose them two at a time.
Notice that flights might not be ordered. Like I might be able to get
from one city to another, but then maybe the airplane has a connection or
something.
So going back is a different cost.
But totally,
there's 2 times 4 choose 2 different pairs
of cities that I could enter or exit from.
OK,
so now what am I going to do?
Well, so
I can compute
the 12 different shortest paths that matter in my
graph. So when I say shortest path, what do I mean?
Well, I'm going
to construct a graph,
G,
with one vertex
per city and one
edge
per flight.
And notice the number of connections that I need to make,
the minimum number between any city and any other city,
is equal to the shortest path, the
length of the shortest path minus 1.
So maybe I have,
here's Boston,
here's London,
here's Paris,
B, L, P for short.
Then the length of my
shortest path
is 2.
And the number of connections I have to
make is 1 because I stopped through London.
So what am I going to do? Well,
for every pair of
cities in this, oops,
no,
that's OK. In the set of the source city
and the three cities you want to visit,
I'm going to compute
the length of the shortest path.
So this is the minimum number of connections I
need to get from any one of these to any other
one in my graph,
G.
Well, how much time does this take? Well,
there's 12 such pairs. We already argued that.
And how much
time does it take to
actually do shortest paths,
say, using breadth -first search?
Linear time the size of the graph. JASON KURIYAMA - Linear time the
size of the graph. I think Jason actually has a t -shirt that says that.
Well, in this case, remember that's big O of the number of edges plus the
number of vertices. But just to make your life a little more annoying,
the
number of vertices is the number of cities,
the number of edges, the number of flights. So this takes 12 times
O of C plus F time, which of course is just O of C plus F time.
Notice this is one of these things where we're being sneaky.
We told you that you specifically visit three places.
And that's where
this number 12 came from.
And if you're going to visit three cities, then
this would be a very different homework problem.
This is one of those things you've got to remember, right?
Where we've given you a few constants and you should use them.
OK.
So now what
can I do? I can iterate
over every permutation
of A, B,
C.
Right?
So this is like saying I go from
my source to city 1, to city 2, to city 3,
back to my source.
Right?
I add
together and compute the cost of
that trip. And remember, cost in this case is
equal to the minimum number of connections.
And then I return the minimizer.
So I say, is it cheaper for me to go Boston, Budapest, Paris, Boston, Paris,
Budapest, and so on. So a for loop over permutations, which generally is
frowned upon. But in this case,
because we told
you you're visiting precisely three places,
how many steps are going to happen in that for loop? Well, we actually
wrote them all out over here on our board. It's exactly 3 factorial, or 6
steps.
3 times 2 times 1, which
is 6. OK?
So right. So at the end
of the day, this for loop is going to take,
well,
order 6 time,
which of course, is just order 1. So it doesn't
really contribute to our runtime at all.
And
our entire algorithm runs in C plus F time.
OK?
So right. So this is one of these problems where you're really taking
advantage of the constants that we gave you. We said you're visiting
three cities, so use it.
Incidentally, as a computer science theorist,
if I said you're visiting exactly 17 cities,
well, what would be our numbers now?
I mean, there would be 17 factorial,
and then like 17 choose 2.
Those are big numbers, but they're still
constants. So for purposes of this class,
that would be OK. But
the second that I gave it a name like m,
then I got to think about those
factorial things a little more carefully.
All right.
So that's this problem. So the basic trick here was that like, yeah, it
looks like all pairs shortest path, but it's not quite. It's all pairs of
things that you're actually going to travel between shortest
path. And since that number of pairs is finite, this is 12,
that's an OK thing to do.
OK.
How are we doing?
Ah, 15 minutes. Perfect.
I didn't want to do the last problem, and I
think I've managed to
get myself in
exactly that position.
OK. So the very last problem on this homework, which again, this homework
really follows the prototypical 6 -006 breadth -first search, depth -first
search homework. I feel
like they all fall into a similar pattern.
Again, all these resources are available to
you guys. You should look at them.
We're not
trying to hide anything.
This problem involves solving a pocket cube, which
is like a little mini Rubik's cube, which is 2 by 2.
And it looks like this.
Ah, there's a star.
Actually,
here we go.
Right. So
here's my Rubik's cube.
Looks like a cube, which
I'm having some trouble drawing.
And in particular, it's 2 by 2,
which makes it a little
easier than your typical Rubik's cube.
OK.
And in
particular, we're going to mark some faces.
Sneakily, they used
a little geometry term here, which is cute.
So
here's face F0. I'm sorry, you can't quite
see that, but
the
top face is F0, in case you were wondering.
The left face
is F1.
And the front -facing face here,
F2.
Notice that we've identified these by vectors that point 90
degrees out from the face. These are called normal vectors.
If you want to define those rigorously, you
can take my grad level class.
But for a
Rubik's cube, it's not terribly difficult.
But in any event, I can talk about flipping this Rubik's cube in a pretty
easy way, which is that I'm going to fix one corner of my cube. So this is
like the
corner that I'm holding onto with my hands.
And now I
can grab, what, the top,
the side, or the
front of my cube. And I can rotate
it clockwise
or counterclockwise.
And you can convince yourself those are all the possible ways that I
could sort of mess with the state of my cube after fixing one corner.
OK?
Right. And so this problem basically is involving a very typical trick. In
fact, a lot of the history of these different search algorithms, breadth
-first search, depth -first search, A star,
which I guess we won't really cover here,
date back to, what, 20, 30 years ago. We
would have called it artificial intelligence.
These days, that has a
very different meaning.
It's all about solving board games and Rubik's cubes and all these kinds
of things using algorithms. And the way that they would do that is by
searching the different
spaces of configurations.
So now, if we think of every
face of this cube as painted with a color,
there are different configurations of my
graph that I get by flipping the three sides.
So if
we think of there being a vertex
for heat
of each state
of my cube,
where state here means the
coloring of every face on my Rubik's cube,
then there's an edge
for every move.
And in this problem, we encoded a move as a
pair J comma S,
where it's saying
that I'm going to rotate
face F of J, where J is between, I guess, 0, 1, and 2
in direction S. And we can just index that as plus or
minus 1 to
say counterclockwise or clockwise.
So this is a cute thing, where your graph has a
bunch of vertices, which are all Rubik's cubes.
That's a cube.
And then there are edges, if I can get from
one to another by doing one of these moves.
And this is a nice abstraction, because if I want to solve a Rubik's cube,
in the most efficient way possible, one way to do that is to compute the
shortest path from my current
configuration to
the platonic Rubik's cube, where all the colors
are constant on the different faces of my cube.
And so that's a basic identification that
happens all over the place in search strategies,
where I'm going to think of every vertex of my graph as being the state
of some system and every edge as being a transition from one to another.
And then paths in this thing are
different ways
of solving my puzzle.
So a different one would be,
I don't know, every vertex is
a chessboard with the chess pieces scattered on the chessboard. And every
edge is one chess move by one player or the other. In that case, you have
to be a little careful, because
you want player 1 or player 2 to go back and forth from each
other. But I'll let you think about the reduction there.
OK, so this problem,
I think, largely is mostly just fun, like combinatorics rather than
algorithms. But there's a little bit of algorithms hiding in here.
So they want you to argue that the number of distinct configurations
of this Rubik's cube, this 2 by 2 guy, is less than 12 million.
This is nice, because 12 million is a number
that computers can actually cope with.
And so there's a
pretty straightforward argument there.
Right, so in particular,
here's a cube.
How many corners are in a cube?
Eight.
Thanks. I hid
one back here, in case you were wondering.
So let's say that I fix
a corner of the cube, like we've done that.
Then every time that I rotate one of the faces of my cube clockwise or
counterclockwise, I'm essentially taking one corner of my cube and sticking it
in another place.
So
in all,
seven corners
of my cube can move.
And if I'm not worried
about like,
it could be that some of these permutations are not actually achievable by
a set of steps, like maybe I'd have to break my Rubik's cube and glue it
back together.
But if
I'm being conservative about it, there's of
course less than or equal to seven factorial
different configurations of the corners.
Right,
so in other words, every time I rotate my face,
one of the corners ends up in a different place.
So there's seven factorial different
ways that that could have happened.
OK, so that's part of my bound. Remember that I'm
trying to bound the total number of configurations here.
And essentially,
what I've done so far is I've said,
OK,
well, there's a bunch of cubes
in my 2 by 2 Rubik's cube. So I'm going to like, unglue this
entire cube. Take just this corner and stick it up here.
And there's like seven factorial different
ways that I could do that.
But I still have to account for the fact that
I pull this piece off, I stick it on the top,
but I have to figure out its orientation. I
can still rotate it about this corner.
And in fact, there are three different ways that I could rotate
it. Right, you can kind of see it. Right, one, two, three.
Yeah,
so in all,
so each corner
can rotate
three ways.
So
that means that I have 3 times 7 factorial
different
configurations as an upper
bound.
And this number is, wait for it,
1, 1, 0, 2,
2, 4, 8, 0.
The problem asks you to argue that your upper bound is upper bounded by
12 million. And indeed, it is less than or equal to 12 million. Is that 3
times 7 factorial or?
Oh, I'm sorry.
Right, because there are seven corners, each of which can rotate three
different ways. So actually, 3 to the seventh power times 7 factorial.
Thank you, student.
OK,
right, so let's see here. Really
quickly moving here, the next problem says,
state the maximum and minimum degree of any
vertex in my graph.
First of all, do I expect
vertices to have different degrees? This is
kind of a goofy problem.
What
would it mean to have a vertex that somehow
has lower degree than another vertex? It would mean that there's some
configuration of this cube for which there are fewer moves that I could do to
change it than a different configuration of
this cube.
And that's obviously not the case. Right,
because when I flip one of the faces of my cube,
all I'm doing is I'm moving the colors around. I haven't
somehow changed the physics of how Rubik's cube works.
And so I
think this was just intended to be annoying by your
instructors. The min degree is equal to the max degree.
And in fact,
the degree
of every node in my graph is constant here.
The one thing that's worth noting here, what I haven't argued, it
turns out, I think, to be true. But what I haven't argued is that I
couldn't rotate a face and
actually end up in the same configuration.
Like maybe for some reason, I have red all the way
around the outside. So when I rotate it, nothing changed.
That obviously isn't true,
but I haven't argued it carefully.
But as long as I don't worry about my graph
being simple, like I'm OK with self loops,
then
the degree is certainly constant.
Yeah?
OK.
And in fact, I don't think
that can happen in a typical Rubik's cube. Well, I think the point is
to say what the degree was. Oh, yeah, indeed. So we haven't computed the
degree, but we've argued that they're equal to one another.
OK, so now we actually have to compute what that degree is.
And here's how
to do it. So of course,
well, this I think is actually even easier
than the first part.
Essentially,
remember, you have three different options
for faces that I
can rotate. I can rotate the top,
the front,
or the
side here. So there's
three faces that we could rotate.
OK, and how many different ways can I rotate them?
I can rotate them counterclockwise or clockwise.
So there's two directions.
So in all, there's degree 6 for every vertex. There's
six different ways in or out of a vertex here.
OK, so the next part of the problem gives you a piece of
code and then does breadth first search on this graph.
And it's super, super slow to give me the
distance to all the other configurations.
And Jason
conveniently has run it on his laptop here.
I'm nervous
to touch your laptop.
I don't care so much,
but I don't want to infect you.
Yeah.
Right. So we have a piece of code that explores
the graph of all the configurations of our cube.
So I do a breadth first search and then gives
me the shortest path, I think, from the base
cube where all the faces are constant to all the other
configurations that are reachable and generates a plot.
Right. And
so what they ask is to
figure out the total
number of configurations that it explores.
One thing that you'll find out,
center down,
is that
it explores pretty much a third.
Exactly a third of all the possible configurations
of my cube. I think we can see that here.
So I guess it runs this
whole thing. You sum them all together.
Right.
Oops.
That's OK.
And so in fact, the kind of fun fact that you can learn about the 2 by 2
by 2 Rubik's cube is that there's actually three connected components in
this graph.
So in other words, there's sort of like three different Rubik's cubes you
can make modulo all the different flips that you can do to the faces. And
those correspond to three corner rotations
of one of the corners of the thing.
OK.
So right. So then the next part of the problem asks you to state the maximum
number of moves needed to solve any Rubik's cube. And you can see it in
this plot. So what this plot is showing you is the size of
the level set of this distance function for every distance.
So I think technically it looks like 0. But actually, this is at a 1
here. We just say there's one vertex at distance 0, which is the source.
And as we move farther and farther out, our tree is
expanding. And we're seeing more and more vertices.
Apparently, most vertices are approximately
distance, what is that, 11 or 12,
11 away from the original. And then eventually,
I explore the entire graph. And I'm done.
And you can
see that the farthest away vertex
is 14 away, meaning that
the most annoying Rubik's cube to solve can be
solved in 14 steps for the 2 by 2 by 2 pocket cube.
I'm sure that Jason probably knows the equivalent of this
number for the 3 by 3 by 3. But I have no idea what it is.
I'm impressed if he can calculate in his
head like he looks like he was about to try.
But I digress.
Right. So in other words, this is actually
a fancy term for,
we talked about the radius of your graph in the
first problem. Now we've got the diameter, which is
well, not necessarily 2 times the radius the way
that we've defined it here, but actually almost,
I think, within some constant of
that.
OK.
So notice
that the vertical axis here is really big.
And this is explaining why this BFS code is so slow, because
these are all the different configurations it has to hit.
Or more accurately, if I take the y position of each one of these
vertices and sum up its height, those are all the configurations that are
touchable,
and those are all
the steps that BFS needs before it's done.
And so that number is in the,
certainly in the millions.
Yeah.
OK. So then the last part of this problem, which it
conveniently looks like I'm low on time to solve,
but I'll
refer you to the solution anyway,
is asking how we
might do this faster.
And so in particular,
what it says is,
let's say that I have a total of n configurations for my Rubik's cube.
In this case, it turns out that that's roughly 3 million, I think.
OK.
And now I want an algorithm
that gives me the shortest
sequence of moves to solve any pocket cube.
Man, I'm
really ravaging the chalk today.
And I want to solve any cube in a number of
steps that looks like 2n
to the ceiling of w over 2,
where, let's see here. The code provides, sorry,
this problem changed on me this afternoon.
Right. So where n sub i is equal to the number
of configurations reachable within i moves.
Oh, good. I
see what we did here.
Right.
So if this is my
base cube, then we've got maybe like a six
different, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6 different cubes that I can reach from those. And then there's six cubes
I can reach from all of those. But of course, some of those might be
pointing backward
or to each other.
But this is the number
of things that are reachable in i moves.
And they ask for an algorithm that
finds the shortest path
in this amount of time.
By the way, big N typically
exponentiates in that subscript there.
This looks
innocent, but it's not.
The basic trick here is to do, I'm not going to bother writing it
down. We'll just talk about it for a second and call it for the day.
No, I'll draw a picture.
So
the breadth first search algorithm that
we've thought about so far chooses a vertex
and then computes level sets
outward from that vertex
until it maybe reaches
the destination
that you want to hit.
That doesn't quite work here. And well, I mean, it does work. But it's going
to be quite slow because let's say I had bad luck and I were in that 14
vertex.
Then somewhere
in there, I'm going to hit this big height,
which is sitting over
the 11, before I can get to the vertex 14.
So the trick here is it turns out
that I can do it by only ever getting to 7.
And the way that I'm going to do
that is instead,
I'm going to run BFS in parallel for two
different vertices, the source and the target.
Current cube and the cube I would like
it to be, like the solution to the problem.
I'm first going to compute the level set 1 of
that cube, then level set 1 of the next cube,
level set 2,
level set 2, 3, 3. And notice that eventually, they're
going to intersect pretty much right at the midpoint.
And so the size of the level set, I never need to compute a level set that's
bigger than half of the shortest path length. I have to round up to be
conservative about that.
And that's where
I get this factor here.
This
little trick for reducing the search size.
This is another kind of standard trick. If you look at some of the code
people use for solving board games algorithmically and so on, I think they
typically
sort of search from the beginning and end state outward and try to meet
in the middle for exactly this reason, which is that exponential growth,
as we all know, can
be quite problematic.
All right, folks. So I think we're just about
out of time. And I've certainly worn myself out.
So with that, hopefully, we'll see you next
week.
Thanks for doing well.